Hello, welcome to 1.0 Foundational
Elements Module Overview.
In this module we're going to cover 1.0
Foundational Elements Module Overview,
which is this video.
1.1 projects, 1.2, the importance of
project management.
1.3, the relationship between project,
program, portfolio and
operations management.
1.4 components of the PIMBOC
guide, 1.5, tailoring, and 1.
6, project management business documents.
Now, I would expect that
you probably became a
project manager in much
the same way that I did.
I was an accidental project manager.
I was a software developer
and so I was an expert
in the specialist work
that had to be performed.
And when a customer wanted
a new system developed,
I was sent to the customer
site for your service.
few weeks to discuss in detail what the
customer wanted and then I would work
alongside the customer to scope the work
and then provide a quote for the cost.
When the customer signed
a contract I would be given
a team a budget and a
deadline and that was it.
I was a technology and business expert but
I was somehow expected to make all this
magical stuff happen within budgets and
within timescales.
So based Basically, my method was to work
really hard day and night.
I worked my team really hard day and out
too.
And if they started to fall behind, then I
would do some of their
specialist work as well.
That's not the way to manage your project,
is it?
My company provided me with what they
called project management software,
but it wasn't.
It was just a program for creating a
project schedule.
It was a good program and project schedule
is an essential tool for any project
manager but it does not somehow manage
projects.
I was required to produce a
project plan for each project and
by project plan they meant a
project schedule or Gant chart.
A project schedule is not a project plan
as we will cover in detail later.
So my projects were completed on time but
my team and I'm were paying the price.
We were slaves to the system.
I began researching project
management and I improved my techniques
and I developed templates and
Excel and in word documents.
But my greatest step
forward of course was when I
discovered the PIMBOC guide
by PMI about 20 years ago.
PIMBOC stands for a guide to the project
management body of knowledge.
This taught me in detail how to do all
sorts of project-related processes,
but I was still lacking an overall
structure and methodology.
Every project manager works out their own
method.
Some are okay, some are bad and some are
worse than useless.
What you need is a reliable, repeatable
method that is due to the test of time and
every industry, every size,
and every type of company,
in every project, in every
country, and every culture.
A method does not expect you as project
manager to work day
and night in panic mode.
And that method is surprisingly Prince 2.
This is a truly generic method that means
it works on any project anyway.
But why am I talking about Prince 2 on a
PMP course?
It's because, as we will discuss later,
the PIMBOC guide is not a methodology.
Does that surprise you?
The PIMBUC guide is very
strong and detailed techniques
but leaves the overall
structure to the project manager.
But Prince 2 is a structure
and it leaves many of
the detailed techniques
to the project manager.
And so a lot of people say to me after
they get to PMP certification, what's next?
how can I advance my career even more?
And so I would suggest once you got your
PMP certification, consider studying for
Prince II and get the Prince II
practitioner certification as well,
and then you will start getting a lot more
job offers.
So we're about to start the very first
lesson, which is 1.1 projects.
Please read the corresponding chapter in
the PINBOC guide
before watching the video.